NOEL BERISTAIN

FRONTEND ENGINEER

noelberistain@gmail.com

Highly experienced and detail-oriented Software Engineer with 7 years of experience in analysis, development, programming, exposure to emerging technologies and software architecture, design and best practices, and agile methodologies. Created efficient solutions as per users and company's requirements. Lately worked as a Front End engineer with strong skills in self-instruction and capable of learning new technologies as required by the project. Specialized in JavaScript, with a preference for web and mobile applications using React.js and React Native. Self-taught professional, always seeking to increase my knowledge and skills in computer science.

TECH STACKS

Frontend:

- React.js, React Native, Next.js, RemixJs
- Javascript (ES6+), Typescript.
- Redux, MobX, Context, Zustand, Redux-Thunk, Hooks, GraphQL, AWS Amplify, AWS Cognito
- Tailwindcss, MUI, Styled Components, CSS3, Html5
- Docker, Webpack, Vite

Backend:

- Node.js
- Express, Nest, Loopback.io
- REST / API
- Microservices
- Require.js
- DayJs, Moment.js, Luxon
- Immutable.js
- Sass
- JWT

Application/Database:

- MongoDB
- Mongoose

Other Tools:

- React Testing Library, Enzyme, Jest
- React Profiler
- Interaction/UX Design
- VS Code
- Agile/Scrum, Kanban
- React Native Debugger
- Git, Bitbucket, Github
- Yarn/Npm/Pnpm
- Design Patterns
- Postman/Insomnia
- Chrome Dev Tools
- Github Copilot

EDUCATION

Ensenada Institute of Technology Bachelor's Degree in Computer Systems Engineering

English level

Advance English (Proficiency)

EXPERIENCE

Distillery (*Software Outsourcing*) Sr Frontend Developer

Oct 2023 - April- 2024

Project: Arteli its an AI analytics interface, based on advanced artificial intelligence and machine learning platform created to function as the central hub for retail executives. Connecting executives with actionable insights, propelling their businesses towards transformation.

- Participate in several meetings with backend and frontend, and stakeholders to talk about tech stack decisions like main UI tech, State management...
- Got involved with documentation around Medusa.js, Remix, and Zustand for starting to work with those following the best practices within our app.
- Create a Medusa.js backend for connecting it to our frontend and fill up our UI with Next Js.
- Follow experienced developers around retail apps that had worked with Medusa.js and switch into Remix as medusa.js documentation recommends.
- Implement Zustand as state management because it looked a faster tech to implement, with some advantages at the point of our app.
- Implement Segment for analytis and connect it with Amplitude.
- Implement sign in and authentication with Autho following docs best practices
- Update and create React components
- Implement some custom hooks

Tech Stacks: React, Typescript, NextJs, Remix, Zustand, TailwindCss

Sr Frontend Developer

Mar 2023 – Oct - 2023

Project: Storefy is an online store management tool, created for help the management teams within every store for knowing where products are located within the store, retrieve and update its information, update commands like remove, add, or move a product, add comments if necessary, all these accomplished by google maps API, taking advantage of its capabilities.

- Great communication with devs, extensive sessions with Design and PO's to get the app in the desired state.
- Involved within a NextJs app and GoogleMaps libraries for displaying store arrangement and products within the map. Utilizing markers and infoWindows and adding functionality to them.
- Lead spike for adding User Management capabilities within the app. Inform the team about my findings and finally implement AWS amplify to connect to AWS Cognito and retrieve user's information.
- Lead spike for implementing User Management, and to add Segment (a CTP) within our app.
- Implement AWS Amplify for user management, and Segment. Always keeping the team informed about the process. And placing documentation about my finding in a dedicated confluence page
- Follow NextJs patterns, implement AG Grid for displaying tables with extensive capabilities, update, and create reusable components with MUI, add unit testing with React testing library
- Change app from NextJs into a simple React app given the product is a B2B.
- Participate in decision of tech stack, architechture and design of the app.
- Implement and fix MUI implementation

Tech Stacks: React, NextJs, Typescript, MUI, Context, Zustand, Redux, AWS Amplify, GoogleApi, Jest, RTL, DevTools, Profile

Sr Frontend Developer

Apr 2022 - March 2023

Project: Build of Altruist, a financial web app developed with top tech technologies and patterns like React.js, GraphQL, REST API, a backend for frontend layer etc., with the purpose of helping users make investments through the platform

- Communicate with the Design team and stakeholders to get a better understanding of the requirements
- Translate required requirements into new components and/or updates to existing parts of our application
- Work following a Kanban methodology, including Scrum meetings and quick calls with my team lead for updates on new priorities
- Create and update new branches and merge pull requests through Bitbucket and Git
- Build a new screen for the web page called Trading, for displaying important information to the
- Worked with tables in HTML5 and AG Grid as an external library
- Perform unit testing with Jest and React Testing Library
- Retrieve data from the backend using GraphQL hooks and queries

Tech Stacks: React, Typescript, CSS3, Html5, Styled Components, Context, Redux, GraphQL, Jest, RTL

NOEL BERISTAIN

FRONTEND ENGINEER

EXPERIENCE

Luxoft (Consultancy)

Oct 2020 – Apr 2022

Software Developer (JavaScript / React)

Project: Build of Intermountain Healthcare+, a web app and a native app for iOS and Android, under Agile/Scrum methodology, including sprint meetings, backlog grooming and planning sessions, trying to meet the proposed deadline and delivery of our work

- Implemented Typescript to support the development and avoid common errors through props and function arguments, defining interfaces for all our components either for our web or RN apps.
- Developed components separately for React and RN, using microservices to retrieve and save information
- Implemented 2 extra meetings to our development life cycle to ensure consistency around what needed to be done, and to make a quick demo
- Worked not only with React Functional Components, but also with some React Class Components
- Used shared modules, since most screens of the web app and the native app use the same data.
- Built most of our components with Material UI and applied them through Styled Components and CSS3 whenever they needed extra styling
- Employed Git as the version control system to manage the commits, and changes to code
- Managed the global state with Redux with defined actions and reducers to complete the state changes
- Used Jest and React Testing Library for unit testing
- Employed Yarn to install and manage all the frontend dependencies
- Created coding standards and company guidelines using TSLint for all TypeScript files
- Have the frontend pull requests reviewed by our senior developers before merging
- Performed code maintenance, removing unused components/variables and refactoring pieces of code to improve app performance
- Used pair programming with team members to accomplish high priority tasks when they are on block release
- Debugged errors with Chrome Development Tools, getting an insight of the current state and our components behavior for web app and React Native apps

Tech Stacks: Typescript, React, RN, Storybook, Material UI, Redux, Jest, React Testing Library, Dev Tools

Sibatel Communications (Consultancy)

UI Developer

Project: Silicon Valley Bank (SVB). Development of a gateway under agile Scrum methodology, with sprint meetings and planning sessions for refinement of the product to meet deadline and delivery.

- Used Typescript to write all the JavaScript code, implementing the latest ECMAScript features with added static type checking to detect errors before runtime
- Held constant communication with the UX team to deliver the expected views and functionality
- Developed multiple React reusable functional components to be used across the app using JSX inside Typescript files
- Leveraged on reacting programming for state management with MobX implementation using observables and avoiding boilerplate
- Implemented styling and code in mobile-first strategy and responsive web design using SASS framework along with SAAS, global variables and modularity in order to avoid collision of styling in components
- Used Jest and Enzyme libraries for unit testing on application components, and Git as a version control system to manage the commits and code changes
- Employed Yarn to Install and manage all frontend and NPM for backend dependencies of the application
- Followed coding standards and company guidelines using TSLint for all Typescript files
- Updated pull requests of frontend code through code reviews by an engineering team
- Implemented React to build the view components of Gateway as a performant single page application that consumes a REST API exposed by the backend server created with LoopBack 4
- Implemented React Hooks in functional components that require some kind of local state-handling
- Enhanced the user experience by providing a minimalist, clear interface with Material UI library
- Performed code maintenance, removing unused components and refactoring pieces of code to improve application performance
- Debugged and solved technical issues

Tech Stacks: Typescript, React, JSX, MobX, SASS, Jest, Enzyme, Yarn

Project: Kenworth. Build of IMS using agile Scrum methodology, taking part in sprint meetings to establish deliverables and deadlines

- Employed Typescript to write all JS code using the latest ES features with added static type checking and detecting errors early through the
- Defined React reusable components using TSX files within the single-page application that consumes a REST API exposed by the backend server
- Centralized the application state using Redux, ensuring a simple data flow through the app, thus a single source of truth
- Performed asynchronous tasks by using Redux-thunk middleware to manage application data, making Axios requests with action creators for the server
- Coded and managed URL navigation of the application with React-Router
- Implemented responsive web design with Bootstrap framework along with media-queries
- Created a Notification System in Node.js along with Socket.io to communicate in real time with other modules
- Applied different design patterns like Module, Singleton, and Observer
- Constructed a MongoDB database, and used Mongoose to define data schemas
- Automated compilation of Typescript files using webpack
- Used Jest testing library for unit testing inside the application and Git as a version control system to manage code changes
- Installed and managed all the app dependencies with NPM
- Followed coding standards and company guidelines using Linters
- Debugged and fixed frontend code through code reviews

Tech Stacks: Typescript, React, JSX, REST API, Redux, Bootstrap, React-Router, Mongo DB, Mongoose, Jest, Git

Jan 2018 – Jun 2020

NOEL BERISTAIN

FRONTEND ENGINEER

EXPERIENCE

TekMexico

Dec 2016 - Dec 2018

Computer Systems Analyst

- Worked under Agile/Scrum methodology
- Implemented MongoDB as the application DB, creating the user model for storing data, validating and authenticating sessions
- Express is as the founding module/layer for including all basic middleware and modules within the application
- Included JWT as an authentication strategy
- Created REST APIs with Express.js
- Leveraged the latest HTML5/CSS3, along with Bootstrap framework for a simple approach solving certain styling demands
- Git as a version control system for back-up and follow-up of the process, keeping everything isolated and tidy
- Maintained the corporate web system, including queries, improvements and view styling, creating new features using cutting-edge web technologies like ES6, React.js, Redux, Bootstrap, JSX, HTML5, CSS3, Node.js, and web sockets
- Planned and designed the application interface according to the desired functionality and user experience
- Analyzed client requirements to find the best approach in data transfer and performance, along with a friendly user interface
- Constructed and timely delivered assigned tasks with high performance and quality, including use of good practices
- Researched new approaches and solutions to software issues, keeping up with the cutting-edge technology stacks
- Participated in daily Scrum meetings with the management and leadership teams, keeping track of current status of tasks in Jira
- Embedded HTML5/CSS3 technologies into preprocessors like Sass to deliver desired looks and feel according to requirements

Tech Stacks: ReactJs, Javascript, NodeJs, MongoDB, Express.js, JWT, REST API, Bootstrap, Git, ES6, Redux, JSX, HTML5, CSS3, Node.js, Websockets